Philip Bankwitz Research Collection
© 2008 University of Connecticut
Philip Bankwitz Research Collection.
undated, 1928-1994, 2004.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Bankwitz, Philip Charles Farwell. (Collector)
3 linear feet.
The collection contains primarily photocopies of correspondence, reports and official documentation of the French government from the 1930s through the end of World War II in 1945. Dr. Bankwitz was a scholr of modern French history at Trinity College (Hartford, CT).
MSS20020116
Biography
Philip C. F. Bankwitz was born 24 February 1924, the son of Charles Edward Bankwitz and Elizabeth Farwell Bankwitz. He was raised in Turners Falls, Massachusetts. He received his education at Harvard University (B.A., 1947; M.A., 1948; Ph.D., 1952). In 1954, he joined the History Department at Trinity College where he spent his career until his retirement in 1969. A scholar of modern France, Dr. Bankwitz' fluency in French made possible his assignment to the French 2nd Armored Division, one of only thirty Americans to serve with this elite unit of the Free French Forces during World War II. For his service to France, he was awarded the French Croix de Guerre.
A long-time resident of Farmington, CT, Dr. Bankwitz died on 21 December 2003.
Published Works:
Maxime Weygand and Civil-Military Relations in Modern France, Harvard University Press, 1967.
Alsatian Autonomist Leaders, Regents Press of Kansas, 1978.
Scope and Content
The collection contains primarily photocopies of correspondence, reports and official documentation of the French government from the 1930s through the end of World War II in 1945. A significant quantity of the photocopies are stamped "Foundation Nationale des Sciences Politiques" and are presumed to have been copied from the papers of Edouard Daladier located in this repository. Most of the materials are in French. In 2008, a 2004 personal tribute of Dr. Bankwitz by Dr. Martin S. Alexander was added to the collection.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by subject. Subject categories were determined as much as possible by the donor's notations (in both French and English).
Series I: Research Collection and Correspondence ( undated, 1928-1994 )
Series II: Personal Papers ( 1928-2004 )
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to World War II. See especially, the Thomas Dodd Papers and Connecticut Soldier's Collection. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Subjects:
Trinity College (Hartford, Conn.) Faculty.; France Politics and government 1940-1945.; France Politics and government 1914-1940.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Photocopies.; Newspapers.; Photographs.
Occupations:
Historian.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Alternative Form Available
Originals of the majority of materials represented in this collection can be found in the Edouard Daladier Papers located at the Foundation Nationale des Sciences Politiques.
Acquisition Information
The materials were donated by Dr. Bankwitz in October 2002. Dr. Bankwitz' monograph collection accompanied the donation. The majority of the titles have been reviewed for inclusion in the University of Connecticut Libraries monograph collection in the Homer Babbidge Library. Dr. Alexander donated his tribute to Dr. Bankwitz in 2008.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Research Collection and Correspondence, undated, 1928-1994
  - "6 Février 1934", undated, 1933 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Allemagne - Russie sabotage, 1939, 1946 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Anglo-French meetings, 1939 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Archives Edouard Daladier Inventaire, 1972 (Box 1:, Folder 5-6)
  - Armements, 1936 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Armements--Riom, 1939-1941 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Armements, 1939-1941 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - Aviation, undated (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - Boheme, Pologne, 1939 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
  - Cagoule Suites, 1938-1940 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
  - Campagne, 1940 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
  - Chars, 1939 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
  - Chars-Riom, undated (Box 1:, Folder 15)
  - COCOS, 1939-1941 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
  - COCOS and Armements, 1938 (Box 1:, Folder 17)
  - Commentary on new books on 1930-1944 period, 1960-1961, 1966 (Box 1:, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1987-1990 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
  - Diplomatie--Italie - Finlande, 1939-1940 (Box 1:, Folder 20)
  - Drôle de guerre, 1939 (Box 1:, Folder 21)
  - Espagne - Pétain, 1939 (Box 1:, Folder 22)
  - Espionnage, 1939 (Box 1:, Folder 23)
  - Government-High Command--Daquier, 1978 (Box 1:, Folder 24)
  - Haut-Commandement and Gouvernement, 1936, 1939 (Box 1:, Folder 25)
  - History 320 Syllabus (Trinity College), 1987 (Box 1:, Folder 26)
  - Honneurs Rôle politique, Post 1945 (Box 1:, Folder 27)
  - Letters, 1944, 1963, 1966 (Box 1:, Folder 28)
  - Lettres diverses du grand publique, 1940-1942 (Box 1:, Folder 29)
  - [loose, unidentified copies], 1938-1940 (Box 1:, Folder 30)
  - [loose, unidentified copies], 1939 (Box 1:, Folder 31)
  - [loose, unidentified copies], 1939 (Box 2:, Folder 32)
  - [loose, unidentified copies], 1948-1984 (Box 2:, Folder 33)
  - Mobilisation, 1939 (Box 2:, Folder 34)
  - Munich, undated (Box 2:, Folder 35)
  - Munich--Daladier, 1938 (Box 2:, Folder 36)
  - Munich--Henri du Kerillis, 1938 (Box 2:, Folder 37)
  - Negotiations, 1939 (Box 2:, Folder 38)
  - North Africa, 1937 (Box 2:, Folder 39)
  - Pacte Allemagne - Russie, 1939 (Box 2:, Folder 40)
  - Plans de mobilisation, 1940 (Box 2:, Folder 41)
  - Poland and decl. war, 1939-1941, 1964 (Box 2:, Folder 42)
  - Procès Flandin (Flandin Trial), undated (Box 2:, Folder 43)
  - Procès instruction (Flandin), 1940-1945 (Box 2:, Folder 44)
  - Protocole Franco-Polonais, 1939 (Box 2:, Folder 45)
  - Purcie [?], 1940, 1960 (Box 2:, Folder 46)
  - Rapport de Chautemps, 1940 (Box 2:, Folder 47)
  - Results Daladier's National defense career, 1930-1940 (Box 2:, Folder 48)
  - Riom, 1941 (Box 2:, Folder 49)
  - Riom--Air, undated (Box 2:, Folder 50)
  - Riom--Depositions, 1936-1940 (Box 2:, Folder 51)
  - Riom--Depositions, 1940 (Box 2:, Folder 52)
  - Russie and Armements Français, 1936-1937 (Box 2:, Folder 53)
  - Sabotage communiste, 1939 (Box 2:, Folder 54)
  - Senat comité secret, 1940 (Box 2:, Folder 55)
  - Supreme War Council, 1939-1940 (Box 2:, Folder 56)
  - Touvier, Paul--War Criminal, 1994 (Box 2:, Folder 57)
  - USSR and Decl. Guerre, 1937-1939 (Box 2:, Folder 58)
  - USSR Pacte, 1937 (Box 2:, Folder 59)
- Series II: Personal Papers, 1928-2004
  - Air personal photographs and certificates, 1928, 1936, 1938, 1984 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Bankwitz, Philip Charles Farwell -- a personal tribute by Martin S. Alexander, 2004 (Box 2:, Folder 60)
  - "Adjustment of a Professional Army to a Democratic Society: France as a test case, 1885-1896,", 1948 January (Box 3:, Folder 61-62)
  - "Evolution of an Anti-Patriot,", 1948 May (Box 3:, Folder 63)
  - "Ruhr-Lorraine: A Study in Industrial Complexes,", 1949 May (Box 3:, Folder 64)
  - "Towards a Manuel Historique in Medieval War,", 1949 January (Box 3:, Folder 65)